Good morning, today's דף *daf* is צדיק טית *Tzadik Tet*, 99. Today's
דף *daf*, and we pick up at the bottom of צדיק חית
עמוד בית *Tzadik Chet Amud Bet*. And actually, for better or worse,
I'll let you decide, we well not leaving the אגדתא *Aggadeta* fully
but we're leaving the immediate אגדתא *Aggadeta* around the פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk*
of תחיית המתים Techiyat Ha-Meisim, *Techiyat Hametim* in עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba,
*Olam Haba* and ימות המשיח Yemot Ha-Mashiach. *Yemot Hamashiach*. Okay, we have
an עמוד *amud* left and then we're going to transition to the
next part of the משנה Mishnah, *mishna*, right? The משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
said the following have no portion in the world to come. So
we've been discussing תחיה *techiyah* and somebody says there's no תחיית המתים
*Techiyat Hametim* from the תורה Torah, *Torah*. So we've been discussing תחיית
המתים *Techiyat Hametim* and עולם הבא olam haba, *Olam Haba* and of
course within that context ימות המשיח Yemos Ha-Mashiach, *Yemot Hamashiach*. And then
we're going to start getting on to the rest of the list.
Somebody says there's no תורה מסיני Torah miSinai *Torah MiSinai* etc., etc.
Okay, so we're going to start that very soon, but we have
one עמוד *amud* still to complete to finish. And we take up
we pick up on the bottom of צדיק חית עמוד בית *Tzadik
Chet Amud Bet*.
Take the let us decide decide what?
Decide whether you think it's for better or for worse. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, first the first of the widest lines. אמר רב Amar Rav:
*Amar Rav*, לא איברי עלמא אלא לדוד *Lo ivrei alma ela l'David*.
The world was created for the sake of דוד David. המלך *David
Hamalech*. ושמואל אמר Amar, *U'Shmuel amar*, not לדווד ושמואל *l'David u'Shmuel*. ושמואל
אמר למשה *U'Shmuel amar l'Moshe*, it was created for the sake of
משה Moshe רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu*. ויוחנן אמר למשיח *V'Yochanan amar l'Mashiach*, for
משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach*. And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to get
into a whole discussion, what's the name of the משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach*?
But I think that this is a fascinating debate, right? In a
way, you actually understand the answer למשה *l'Moshe* the best, which is
the classic sort of rabbinic approach, right? The world was created for
תורה Torah *Torah*, for us to learn תורה Torah *Torah*, for us
to do מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot*. משיח Mashiach *Mashiach* you also understand, right?
That ultimately we reach a time of of you know of final
like redemption or you know like a greater perfect perfected world is
the sense of like the messianic time. Okay, so but what's the
idea of לדוד *l'David*?
Maybe תפילה *tefillah*, you know.
Oh, that's interesting. דוד David, *David* in terms of like תהילים *Tehillim*
and תפילה *tefillah* because we've had a whole theme before about oh
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says דוד David. *David* with תפילה *tefillah*?
Oh, I just I didn't see oh בזכות תשבחות שהיה אומר לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא *Bizchut tishbachot she'haya omer lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu*. Thank
you. I even forgot רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* there. Oh, that's nice. So
you have תפילה *tefillah*, תורה Torah *Torah*, and like more of a
תיקון עולם *tikkun olam* perfected world. I was actually thinking about דוד
David? *David* in that's very nice. I was actually thinking about דוד
David? *David* in sort of comparison and contrast to משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*
because דוד David *David* is also like משיח Mashiach? *Mashiach* is משיח
Mashiach בן דוד Ben David, *Mashiach ben David*, right? But דוד David
*David* is more sort of like an imperfect like you know it's
still within the more imperfect world, right? It's sovereignty, it's a king,
a king who who you know who's righteous, of course he sins
too, right? I mean you know come on with בת שבע *Bat
Sheva* all those things he does תשובה teshuvah. *teshuva*, right? So it's
sort of like are we living our lives to get to that
future perfect reality, you know, or maybe the goal actually is is
to live the most perfect or the least imperfect life you know
that we can in this world you know without sort of that
envision of like the future more perfect world? Sort of like the
רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*, אין בין עולם הזה לימות המשיח אלא שיעבוד מלכויות
*Ein bein olam hazeh l'yemot Hamashiach ela shiubud malchuyot*. So I think
it's interesting thinking about the contrast, right? Between דוד David *David* and
משיח Mashiach, *Mashiach*, which could be like variations on a theme but
how much is it about something you know more perfect or how
much is it like no, the best we can in the imperfect
world in which we live. Okay, so anyway now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* switches to say ומה שמו *U'mah shemo*? What's משיח Mashiach, *Mashiach*'s
name? So this is a very cute גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. דבי רבי
Rebbe, שילה אמרי שילה שמו *Debei Rabbi Shila amri Shilo shemo*. So
the house of רבי שילה *Rabbi Shila* says שילה שמו *Shilo shemo*,
his name is שילה *Shilo*, right? They're making it after their own
name. Okay, שנאמר shene'emar עד כי יבוא שילה *Shene'emar ad ki yavo
Shilo*, until שילה *Shilo* comes. Okay. דבי רבי ינאי אמרי ינון שמו
*Debei Rabbi Yannai amri Yanun shemo*. ינאי ינון *Yannai Yanun*, his name
is ינון שמו *Yanun shemo*, שנאמר shene'emar *shene'emar*, as it says, יהי
שמו לעולם le'olam? לפני שמש ינון שמו *Yehi shemo l'olam lifnei shemesh
Yanun shemo*, let his name be forever before the sun his name
is ינון *Yanun*, before like the sun yet we had a whole
vision before about how the sun will be brighter and so on,
so before that period. Okay, המשיח *Hamashiach* will come. דבי רבי חנינא
אמרי חנינא שמו *Debei Rabbi Chanina amri Chanina shemo*. His name is
חנינא *Chanina*, שנאמר shene'emar אשר לא אתן לכם חנינה *shene'emar asher lo
eten lachem chanina*, okay, that I still have not given you חנינה
*chanina*. ויש אומרים *V'yesh omrim*, and some say, מנחם בן חזקיה שמו
*Menachem ben Chizkiyah shemo*, שנאמר she'ne'emar כי רחק ממני מנחם *shene'emar ki
rachak mimeni menachem*. Okay,
now that ויש אומרים *v'yesh omrim* might still be a variation of
רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*, מנחם *Menachem*, משיב נפשי *meshiv nafshi*. Okay,
so he's still distanced from us. Okay. ורבנן אמרי *V'rabanan amri*, and
the rabbis say, so again what is the point of doing all
of this? It's not clear but we're going to see in a
minute, you know, it might sort of be echoing back the idea
before about like about like you know when will he come? Today,
אם בקולו תשמעו *im bekolo tishma'u*. So you know if these are
like it's not רב שילה *Rav Shila* said his name is שילה
*Shilo*, it's the house of רב שילה *Rav Shila*, the house of
רב ינאי *Rav Yannai*, right? So maybe it's like each one of
these schools is saying our רבי *rebbe* in theory could be the
משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*. Okay, right? You know now that could get dangerous,
right? If it goes from the in theory to is, right? The
משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach*, but nevertheless you know that sense of like it's
it we can anticipate it any you know there are people nowadays
who in theory have that potential. So it's cute this idea about
like naming it like identifying their רבי *rebbe* as the one. ורבנן
אמרי *V'rabanan amri*, and the rabbis say... חיוורא דבי רבי שמו. No,
no, it is the lepers or the sick of the house of
רבי, we're going back to the idea of him being a sickly
person, a suffering servant, שנאמר she'ne'emar אכן חלינו הוא נשא, achen cholyenu
hu nasa, our illnesses he bears, ומכאובנו סבלם, umachovenu sevelam, and
our wounds he suffered, ואנחנו חשבנוהו נגוע ומוכה אלהים ומעונה, va'anachnu chashavnuhu
nagua umukeh elohim ume'uneh,
we have considered him to be a leprous one, smitten by God
and afflicted. Okay, so that's again the image of the afflicted
משיח. mashiach, אמר רבי נחמן: Amar Rabbi Nachman: אם מן חייא הוא,
im min chayya hu,
if he is one, if he is somebody living, okay, and רש"י
Rashi has two versions, like are we actually identifying who he might
be or if he's comparable to somebody who is living, right, gets
back, but it's obviously echoing some of that idea we had just
a minute ago. So כגון אנא, kegon ana, I would be a
good example of who could be משיח. mashiach Now why is he
saying that? Is it a little like give yourself a nice little
pat on the back there, okay, but
also the מהרש"א Maharsha points out, right, that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
was close, was like had a position of political
leadership, so the idea again that משיח mashiach is also a political
leader and a head of the Jews. Okay, so somebody like me,
שנאמר she'ne'emar והיה אדירו ממנו ומשלו מקרבו יצא, vehaya adiro mimenu umoshlo
mikirbo yetzei, the glorious one will be him and the ruler will
come from their midst. So, here I am, I have political power
and I'm from within the Jewish people and so on.
It doesn't sit well with being מנוגע ומוכאשכין. minugam umukashchin.
I know, so these are different visions and they don't all reconcile,
Michael. אמר רב: אם מן חייא הוא im min chayya hu כגון
רבינו הקדוש, kegon Rabbeinu Hakadosh, if he is like one of somebody
who is living, it would be like רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda
Hanasi, right, that's a perfect example, religious and political leader. אם מן
מתיא הוא, im min metaya hu, if he's comparable to somebody who
has already passed away, כגון דניאל איש חמודות, kegon Daniel ish chamudot,
דניאל Daniel also, right, he was a religious leader, he was given
power, I mean, he was given not dominion over the
Jews, power in the non-Jewish political system, but obviously it's an interesting
mix of those
qualities. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: Is
דניאל Daniel actually called איש חמודות ish chamudot in the תורה, Torah
is that the נביא Navi or is
it just like that's a rabbinic appellation? Yeah,
what does it say? He's called איש חמודות. ish chamudot.
Yeah, there's a verse somewhere, yeah,
there you go.
Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: עתיד
הקדוש ברוך הוא להעמיד להם דוד אחר, atid hakadosh baruch hu leha'amid
lahem David acher,
there will be another דוד. David, So not only a son of
King דוד, David but he will be another דוד. David. What does
that mean? Does it mean his name will be דוד? Does it
mean that he will be somehow in some ways a copy of
King דוד? Okay, שנאמר she'ne'emar as the verse says, ועבדו את ה'
אלהיהם ואת דוד מלכם אשר אקים להם, ve'avadu et Hashem eloheihem ve'et
David malkam asher akim lahem, and they will serve ה' Hashem their
God and דוד their king that I will raise up for them.
הקים לא נאמר אלא אקים, heikim lo ne'emar ela akim, that I
have risen up it does not say, but I will raise. אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי: Amar lei Rav Papa le'Abaye: והכתיב, ve'hakativ, but
doesn't it say, ודוד עבדי נשיא עליהם, veDavid avdi nasi aleihem, he
will be a prince, a prince is not the same as a
king, לעולם? So the גמרא Gemara. says no, כגון קיסר ופלגי קיסר,
kegon Keisar upalgi Keisar, no, what you have is the Caesar and
the half-Caesar. So yes, so
fine, King דוד there will be, משיח mashiach will be בן יוסף,
Ben Yosef, so it's not exactly, so if you look at רש"י,
Rashi רש"י Rashi says כגון קיסר ופלגי קיסר, kegon Keisar upalgi Keisar,
מלך ושני לו, melech veshani lo, כן דוד החדש מלך ken David
hachadash melech כדכתיב kid'kativ דוד מלכם אשר אקים David malkam asher akim
ודוד המלך שני לו. veDavid hamalech sheni lo.
So the resurrected King דוד will be the second in command, the
executive vice-king, and the newly born דוד, again, I don't know what
the point is calling him a new דוד rather than just calling
him a בן דוד, okay, again, maybe he'll be similar in ways
to דוד. Anyway, he will be the king. All right, I don't
know what exactly the point of all that is. Okay, אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי: Amar lei Rav Papa le'Abaye: והכתיב, ve'hakativ, and doesn't
it, I just did that. Okay, דרש רב שמלאי: Darash Rav Simlai:
מאי דכתיב, mai de'kativ,
what's meant by the verse, הוי המתאוים את יום ה', hoi hamit'avim
et yom Hashem, woe to those
who yearn for the day of God. למה זה לכם יום ה',
lama zeh lachem yom Hashem, why are you yearning for the day
of God? It's like the גמרא Gemara before about חבלי משיח, chevlei
Mashiach, okay, הוא חשך ולא אור, hu choshech velo or, it'll be
a day of darkness, not light, which again could mean the period
prior to the Messianic era. So he says, משל לתרנגול ועטלף, mashal
letarnagol ve'atalev,
so it's like consider you had a rooster and a bat שהיו
מצפים לאור, she'hayu metzapim la'or, they were both in the middle of
the night and they were both expecting daybreak anytime soon. אמר ליה
תרנגול לעטלף: Amar lei tarnagol la'atalev: אני מצפה לאור שאור שלי הוא,
ani metzapeh la'or she'or sheli hu,
I understand why I'm waiting for daybreak, that's my time, I get
to, the rooster crows in the morning etc. right, that's the time
that I
am a diurnal animal, is it diurnal? Is that the opposite of
nocturnal? Yes, I think so, diurnal animal, ואתה למה לך אור, ve'ata
lama lach or, why are you the bat... waiting for light, the
light isn't going to be good for you. והיינו דאמר ליה. Ve-hainu
d'amar lei. So anyway, the point is, it is a day of
darkness, but a day of darkness to those who will be punished,
meaning it's not the—the גמרא's Gemara. not reading this as חבלי משיח
Chevlei Mashiach or even the righteous suffer. It's reading this as the
period of the messianic period where the righteous are rewarded, but why
are you, the wicked, looking for the time of משיח? mashiach That's
going to be a bad time for you. You're like the bat
when the light comes. Okay. דף צ"ט עמוד א. Daf Tzadi-Tet Amud
Alef. והיינו דאמר ליה ההוא מינא לרבי אבהו. Ve-hainu d'amar lei ha-hu
mina le-Rabbi Abbahu.
That's like that מין Min said to רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. אימתי
אתי משיח? Eimatai ati Mashiach? When will משיח mashiach? come? אמר ליה.
Amar lei. לכי חפי להו חשוכא להנהו אינשי. Lichi chafi le-hu chashocha
le-hanei inshi. When
darkness covers those people, meaning you guys, you know, you sectarians or
apostates or whatever. אמר ליה. Amar lei. מילט קלייט לי? Milat kalait
li? Are you cursing me? אמר ליה. Amar lei. קרא כתיב. Kra
ktiv. Basically, well yeah, but okay, it's a פסוק. pasuk. כי הנה
החשך יכסה ארץ וערפל לאומים. Ki hinei ha-choshech yechaseh eretz va-arafel le-umim.
Darkness will cover the land and you know, thick darkness, thick clouds
the nations. ועליך יזרח השם. Ve-alayich yizrach Hashem.
On you God will shine forth. וכבודו עליך יראה. U-chevodo alayich yeira-eh.
All right. תניא רבי אליעזר. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer. ימות המשיח. Now that
we've dealt with the issue about חבלי משיח Chevlei Mashiach which was
sort of
yesterday, and then this question about like who's named משיח, Mashiach who
in theory could be the משיח, Mashiach etc. Now we're getting to
how long would the messianic period be leading into, because after the
messianic period we're going to have עולם הבא, olam haba remember? Okay,
so תניא. Tanya. רבי אליעזר אומר ימות המשיח ארבעים שנה. Rabbi Eliezer
omer yemot ha-mashiach arbaim shana. 40 years. שנאמר ארבעים שנה אקוט בדור.
She-ne'emar arbaim shana akut be-dor. For 40 years I have seized the
generation. Why we assume that has to do with משיח is not
clear. רש"י Rashi tries to explain like he means a special generation
so you know, or it could be דור המדבר. Dor ha-midbar. What?
Well, it is דור המדבר Dor ha-midbar פשט. Pshat. רש"י Rashi acknowledges
that. Anyway, but he just says, you know, I will like seize
them, meaning I will be king over them for 40 years. And
then will be the new period. Okay. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר
שבעים שנה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah omer shivim shana.
70 years. שנאמר והיה ביום ההוא ונשכחת צור שבעים שנה. She-ne'emar ve-haya
ba-yom ha-hu ve-nishkachat tzor shivim shana. That day Tyre will be forgotten
for 70 years. כימי מלך אחד. Ki-ymei melech echad. Like the period
of one king. איזהו מלך המיוחד? Eizehu melech ha-meyuchad? So the גמרא
Gemara. says what is the unique, distinctive king? הוי אומר זה משיח.
Hevei omer zeh Mashiach. So in passing, the verse is indicating that
the reign of the special king will be for 70 years. Okay.
רבי אומר שלשה דורות. Rabbi omer shlosha dorot. Three generations. שנאמר ייראוך
עם שמש. She-ne'emar yira-ucha im shemesh. They will see you
with the sun. Again, the sun is like the messianic period. ולפני
ירח. Ve-lifnei yarei-ach. And before the moon. So again, like exactly. The
moon is like maybe רש"י Rashi, says, I think, what does he
say? Yeah, מלכות דבית דוד. Malchut d'veit David. The
moon represents the kingdom of בית דוד. Beit David. Okay. דור דורים.
Dor dorim. Generation, generations. So one generation plus two is three generations.
Now, once we have the messianic period going for more than a
simple generation, are we assuming that that means that people will live
for a super long time in that period? Or does that just
mean that no, not that מלך משיח Melech Mashiach will live for
that long? He'll die, his son will rule, etc. And this is
a messianic period, okay? So that's I think that's left open. רבי
הילל אומר. Rabbi Hillel omer. Now we saw this the other day.
רבי הילל Rabbi Hillel says, אין להם משיח לישראל. Ein lahem mashiach
le-yisrael.
Nah, there's not going to be any משיח. שכבר אכלוהו בימי חזקיה.
She-kvar achaluhu bi-ymei Chizkiyahu.
Chizkiyahu was the fulfillment of all those prophecies. He was the person
that all the prophets were prophesying about. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav
Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, שרי ליה מאריה לרבי הילל.
Shrei lei mareih le-Rabbi Hillel.
His Master should forgive רבי הילל. Rabbi Hillel. God should forgive you
for such an error statement, such a wrongheaded statement. חזקיה אימת הוי
בבית ראשון. Chizkiyahu eimat havah be-vait rishon. Chizkiyahu was in the first
בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. But so many of the messianic prophecies are
after that period. Okay. ואילו זכריה. Ve-ilu Zechariah.
And זכריה. Zechariah. This was not the זכריה Zechariah who was killed
in the first בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. It was
זכריה מלאכי—the Zechariah Malachi זכריה Zechariah of the prophets who came back
in the second בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. קא מתנבי בבית שני. Ka
mitnabi be-vait sheini. He was prophesying in the times of בית שני.
Bait Sheini. ואמר. Ve-amar. And he said, גילי מאד בת ציון. Gili
me-od bat Tzion.
Rejoice greatly, daughter of Zion. הריעי בת ירושלים. Hari-ee bat Yerushalayim. You
know, shout forth, daughter of Jerusalem. הנה מלכך יבא לך. Hineh malkeich
yavo lach. Your king will still come. צדיק ונושע הוא עני ורכב
על חמור. Tzadik ve-nosha hu ani ve-rochev al chamor.
The whole you know, whole poor person riding on the donkey. That's
the vision of זכריה. Zechariah. ועל עיר בן אתונות. Ve-al ayir ben
atonot. And on a whatever, also
a donkey, the son of a female donkey. Okay? I don't know
what he would
say. Now, of course, the other question is, what does he think?
He thinks that there's not going to be any עולם הבא, olam
haba like there's no future period of a redeemed world in his
vision? So if you look at Rashi, right, Rashi says, אין להם
משיח לישראל, ein lahem mashiach l'yisrael,
about ten lines down in the narrow lines on the right hand
side, אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא ימלוך בעצמו ויגאלם
לבדו. ela hakadosh baruch hu yimloch b'atzmo v'yigaleim l'vado. So he's not
denying that there's going to be, right, well yeah, but also that's
the whole question of is it from above or from below. So
Rashi can't believe that he basically fundamentally disagrees with this sort of
eschatological vision, right, and that might be a partial explanation to how
he answers these verses that, you know, see a messianic period. He
says but it's not going to be a this-worldly king, right, it's
not going to be a new King David, right, so it almost
sounds like we're going to like jump straight to the עולם הבא
olam haba period, you know, it's not going to be as, you
know, it's not even going to be through a human king, we're
going to be directly with God as our king. So does that
mean again, like straight to an עולם הבא Olam Haba. period with
a transformed world? You know, does it mean that like maybe it
fits in with the good whole idea of like a democracy, you
know, we're not going to need a king in the future, we're
going to be, you know, be able to worship God directly, but
it doesn't mean a different type of a world, it just means
that we'll, you know, whatever, won't need a king to help us
do that.
It means we're on a higher level really.
Right, or something like that. Anyway, it still is pretty strange. And
look, this idea that there's this Rabbeinu Hillel that rejects the idea
of that there's a משיח, okay, I mean if you think about
what are the things that אין להם חלק לעולם הבא, ein lahem
cheilek l'olam haba, right, משיח isn't mentioned, right? האומר אין תחיית המתים
מן התורה ha'omer ein techiyat hameitim min hatorah and אין תורה מן
השמים, ein torah min hashamayim,
what was it? That's basically an אפיקורוס, apikoros, okay.
So אפיקורוס apikoros
is, well we'll see what אפיקורוס apikoros means. אפיקורוס apikoros in the
Rambam means something much broader than it means in the גמרא. Gemara,
So anyway, so the idea, this led as I mentioned the other
day to an interesting question, right, which is that does that mean
that dogma can be פסק? paskened? Like okay, in the גמרא Gemara
you never have the idea of a belief in a משיח as
being some central part of אמונה. emunah. Obviously it's, you know, but
in later the Rambam or whatever, you know, these ideas become part
of what's considered classic dogma. And if you don't believe in משיח
then that it will come, then, you know, what are you? Then
you're an אפיקורוס apikoros and what are the whole consequences of that,
etc. Now a lot of that gets developed in Rambam and it's
not clear in the גמרא. Gemara But it raises an interesting question
about how could you have a debate about it? So you know,
David Bleich who wrote this book In Perfect Faith, which is a,
which is a compendium of like all the different positions of the
ראשונים rishonim on the י"ג עיקרי אמונה, yud gimmel ikarei emunah, in
his introduction, if I'm remembering correctly, he basically discusses this issue of
the position of Rabbeinu Hillel and says basically yeah, like, you know,
אמונה emunah can be פסק. paskened. And that it's fine, we פסק
paskened against him. And therefore, you know, and now, now it is
a כפירה kefirah to deny that there's a משיח and you are
an אפיקורוס. apikoros. Before we פסק paskened that way, Rav Hillel wasn't
that way, but now it is. You know, Marc Shapiro, you know,
sort of disagrees, you know, has written on issues of faith and
dogma, whatever, and he says you know, obviously the assumption about dogma
is not a question about like deciding how to act but it's
a question about eternal truths, and either they are true or they're
not true, you know. So that could be, meaning it could be
that we've decided that Hillel was wrong. The question is, you know,
and so it's not the פסק, psak, meaning it could be that
we're saying that Rabbeinu Hillel, this, that this Rabbi Hillel was always
wrong. It's not like before we פסק paskened he wasn't wrong and
now he is wrong. It could be he always was wrong as
a matter about what actually is going, you know, what the right
beliefs are, what actually is going to happen. But still the question
is that does the question of the consequence of not having the
right beliefs, is that a matter of פסק, psak, right? You understand,
there's two questions, like what are the right beliefs, right, you know,
and are they objectively true or not? That obviously you want to
say of course, you know, one presumably these are questions of whether
they're objectively true or not, right? Even things that are future oriented.
On the other hand, whether there's an idea of פסק psak in
terms of what are the consequences of having wrong dogma and wrong
beliefs. Anyway, it's a real interesting question seeing that, now Rabbeinu Hillel
was not a, Rav Hillel was not a major figure in the
גמרא. Gemara I challenge you to find where else Rav Hillel gets
quoted anywhere else in ש"ס. Shas. He's a minor figure. But nevertheless,
it's not so much like a major figure held this, you know,
unorthodox opinion, it's that the גמרא, Gemara you know, doesn't treat it
with any big horror. Oh my god, how could somebody say there's
never going to be a משיח? Like you know, God should forgive
you for saying such a stupid thing. And the only rejection was
'cause you know there's a פסוק. pasuk I mean, so the גמרא
Gemara doesn't react to it in this horrific way. So it's interesting
thinking about the significance of that in terms of issues of, you
know, a range of, you know, when there are debates about issues
of dogma, etc. Okay, anyway, so now we continue. תניא אידך, tanya
idach, it was taught in another braisa. Rabbi Eliezer says, ימות המשיח
ארבעים שנה, yemos hamashiach arbaim shana, forty years, כדכתיב kideichtiv it says,
ויענך וירעיבך, vaya'anchecha vayarivecha,
God afflicted you and made you starved, ויאכילך. vaya'achilecha. and he fed
you the מן, man, so that was for forty years. וכתיב התם
u'chsiv hasam שמחנו כימות עניתנו, samcheinu kiyemos inisanu, rejoice,
make us rejoice like the days of our affliction, שנות ראינו רעה,
shanos rainu ra'ah, the days that we have saw evil. So those
days were forty and the assumption is that forty days transfers into
forty years. Now why forty days transfers into forty years is like
the מרגלים, meraglim, יום לשנה, yom l'shanah, although רש"י Rashi says some
have the גירסא girsa that it was forty thousand years because of
the idea that a day of God is a thousand years. Alright,
see, anyway, so we're, some
people say משיח will be forty thousand years. Yeah, we'll see something
close to that in a minute. רבי דוסא אומר Rabbi Dosa omer
ארבע מאות שנה, arba meos shanah, four hundred years. כתיב הכא ksiv
hacha ועבדום וענו אותם ארבע מאות שנה v'avadum v'inu osam arba meos
shanah וכתיב התם u'chsiv hasam שמחנו כימות עניתנו. samcheinu kiyemos inisanu.
So the days of our affliction is four hundred years. רבי אומר
Rabbi omer ג' מאות וששים וחמש שנה, gimmel meos v'shishim v'chamesh shanah,
three hundred and sixty-five years, כמנין ימות החמה, k'minyan yemos hachama, like
the days of the solar year, שנאמר she'ne'emar, כי יום נקם בלבי,
ki yom nakam b'libbi, a day of vengeance is in my heart,
ושנת גאולי באה, u'shnas geulai ba'ah, and the year of my redemption
is come. מה יום, ma yom, so anyway, and again an assumption
of one day per year. Of course here רש"י, Rashi oh actually
it wasn't רש"י Rashi before had the forty thousand, I made a
mistake, here רש"י Rashi has the גירסא girsa that has three hundred
and sixty-five thousand. Okay,
same idea though, do you transfer a day to a year or
a day to a thousand years? Alright, okay. מה יום נקם בלבי?
ma yom nakam b'libbi? אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan ללבי גליתי
לאברי לא גליתי. l'libbi gilis' l'eivarai lo gilis'.
I have revealed it to my heart but not to my, you
know, to my limbs, meaning I haven't even said to myself what
that day of future redemption will be, it is so secret. In
a way, you know, God isn't even acknowledging it to God's self,
to just show how, you know, impossible it is to anticipate and
how hidden it is. ריש לקיש אומר Resh Lakish omer ללבי גליתי
למלאכי השרת לא גליתי. l'libbi gilis' l'malachei hashareis lo gilis'.
Maybe a little less hidden. No, I've let my heart know but
I didn't let the angels know. Like, okay, I've admitted it to
myself, I haven't told it to anybody else. But still they're talking
about like how hidden this day is. תניא אבימי בריה דרבי אבהו
Tanya Avimi brei d'Rabbi Abbahu ימות המשיח לישראל שבעת אלפים שנה, yemos
hamashiach l'yisrael shivas alafim shanah, seven thousand years. Okay so here it's
explicit. If before it was a question of גירסאות, girsaos, here at
least you're already getting into the thousands of years. שנאמר she-ne'emar ומשוש
חתן על כלה ישיש עליך אלקיך, u'msos chasan al kallah yasis alaich
elokaich,
like the rejoicing of a חתן chasan on a כלה, kallah, so
the same way there are seven days of the, you know, שבע
ברכות sheva brachos and ימי המשתה, yimei hamishteh, so one day per
thousand years. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
ימות המשיח כיום שנברא העולם ועד עכשיו. yemos hamashiach k'yom she'nivra ha'olam
v'ad achshav.
The messianic period will be the same period of world history until
now from the creation of the world. So five thousand seven hundred
and whatever depending on when he comes. שנאמר she-ne'emar, כימי השמים על
הארץ. ki'yemei hashamayim al ha'aretz. Right, so what's that פסוק pasuk? is,
what's the פסוק? passuk. It says, למען ירבו ימיכם וימי בניכם על
האדמה אשר נשבע ה' לאבתיכם לתת להם כימי השמים על הארץ, l'maan
yirbu yimeichem v'yimei vineichem al ha'adamah asher nishba Hashem la'avoseichem lases lahem
k'yimei hashamayim al ha'aretz,
that your days should be increased, right? So that's being read here
as like when you're all doing the מצוות and a future period,
a messianic period, and your days will be as long as the
days of שמים על
הארץ, shamayim al ha'aretz, the entire length of world history. Now again,
the fact that that means ירבו ימיכם, yirbu yimeichem, your days will
increase, is that suggesting that that means that people will live that
long? Right, is this a messianic era, epoch, that people will still
live and die in a natural way, you know, like or whatever,
maybe they'll live a little bit longer? Or does that mean when
we're saying it's going to be seven thousand years or five thousand
years or whatever we're saying, is that a suggestion that that's how
long people will live? That's not clear. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak omer כימי נח ועד עכשיו, ki'yemei Noach v'ad
achshav, which isn't a big difference than the previous answer, from the
period of נח Noach until now. שנאמר She-ne'emar: כי מי נח זאת
לי אשר נשבעתי מעבור מי נח עוד על הארץ. ki mei Noach
zos li asher nishbati me'avor mei Noach od al ha'aretz. This will
be like the days of נח Noach עוד על הארץ. od al
ha'aretz. So the way רש"י Rashi says this is that the world
will not be destroyed, right? God takes an oath until a period
the length of the period from נח Noach until now passes, right?
Because remember after the messianic period the world gets destroyed and עולם
הבא Olam Haba gets recreated. Okay, so it's saying that, and
the oath by נח Noach was God wouldn't destroy the world. So
the reading is that when משיח comes there'll be a period of
that long of world history and then God will destroy the world
once, okay. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן
amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan כל הנביאים כולם לא נתנבאו אלא לימות המשיח.
kol hanevi'im kulam lo nisnab'u ela l'yimos hamashiach.
All of the visions in the prophets were for the, you know,
and they view like, you know, the lion will lie down with
the, what does the lion might lie down with, the כבש keves
with the lamb or whatever, they'll beat their bows into, their swords
into plowshares. So all of those visions are the messianic period. אבל
לעולם הבא, aval l'olam haba, but
when it comes to the world to come, the world that will
be afterwards, that'll be like the truly, you know, miraculous existence. In
that case, עין לא ראתה אלקים זולתך, ayin lo ra'asah Elokim zulasecha,
no eye has seen that God, like not even the prophetic eye
has seen it, only You God know what that time will be.
יעשה למחכה לו, ya'aseh l'mechakeh lo, You will do for the one
who longs for it. ופליגא דשמואל, u'pliga d'Shmuel, this argues on שמואל.
Shmuel. דאמר שמואל d'amar Shmuel אין בין העולם הזה לימות המשיח אלא
שעבוד מלכויות. ein bein ha'olam hazeh l'yimos hamashiach ela shibud malchuyos. Like
שמואל Shmuel says, there is no difference between this world and the
world to come except rather we are subjugated to foreign powers. Okay,
so for שמואל, Shmuel, the messianic period is very this-worldly, so the
visions of the prophets are oriented to עולם הבא. Olam Ha-Ba, But
according to the other opinion, no, the Messiah's period is miraculous and
the visions of the prophets are the messianic period, and עולם הבא
Olam Ha-Ba, you can't even begin to describe what that will be.
ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, v'omar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba omar Rabbi Yochanan, כל הנביאים לא נתנבאו אלא לבעלי תשובה. kol
hanevi'im lo nisnabu ela l'ba'alei teshuvah. All of the visions of the
prophets and the amazing things that would happen, let's say in the
messianic period, that was only for the people that had sinned and
then done תשובה. אבל צדיקים גמורים, aval tzaddikim gemurim, those that had
never sinned, עין לא ראתה אלקים זולתך. Ayin lo ra'asa Elokim zulasecha.
That, they haven't even begun
to,
they had no vision of that, not even through their prophetic eye,
you know, what that reward will be and what that world will
be. ופליגא דרבי אבהו. U'pliga d'Rabbi Abbahu. So now, giving a higher
status to the צדיקים גמורים tzaddikim gemurim over the בעלי תשובה ba'alei
teshuvah argues on רבי
אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. דאמר רבי אבהו, d'omar Rabbi Abbahu, מקום שבעלי תשובה
עומדים שם צדיקים אינם עומדים. makom she'ba'alei teshuvah omdim sham tzaddikim einam
omdim. The place where the בעלי תשובה ba'alei teshuvah stand, that will
be even at a higher place, the fully righteous will never stand,
שאינם עומדים שם, she'einam omdim sham, שנאמר, She-ne'emar: שלום שלום לרחוק ולקרוב.
shalom shalom l'rachok v'lakarov. Peace,
peace to the distant and to the near. So ברישא רחוק, b'reisha
rachok,
first peace goes to those who started off as distant, okay, והדר
קרוב, v'hadar karov,
and then to those that are near. מאי רחוק? Mai rachok? רחוק
דמעיקרא. rachok d'meikara. So רחוק rachok doesn't mean currently distant, but those
that started distant and have drawn near, the בעלי תשובה. ba'alei teshuvah.
ומאי קרוב? u'mai karov? קרוב דמעיקרא והשתא, karov d'meikara v'hashta, okay, those
that have always been until now and until now have always been
close. But first peace is extended to those that have only drawn
close now and have been near in the past.
So do you get the idea from right this verse or is
it in other places as well?
Yeah, you mean does he quote other proof texts for this idea?
I mean if the righteous don't stand?
I mean this is an idea that is quoted in multiple places,
you know, but yes, it's all the same quote. Okay, okay.
ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan omar, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who
says that the צדיקים גמורים tzaddikim gemurim are at a higher level,
לרחוק שרחוק מעבירה. l'rachok she'rachok me'aveirah. No, רחוק rachok does not mean
was distant from God, it means somebody that was always distant from
sin.
קרוב שקרוב מעבירה ונתרחק הימנו. karov she'karov me'aveirah v'nisracheik heimenu. And קרוב
karov means who gets the peace after is the one who has
been close to sin and only now has distanced from it. Not
a great read of the פסוק. Pasuk Okay, ואמר רבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, v'omar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba omar Rabbi Yochanan,
כל הנביאים כולם לא נתנבאו אלא משיא בתו לתלמיד חכם. kol hanevi'im
kulam lo nisnabu ela masi bito l'talmid chacham. All of these prophetic
visions were for people that supported Torah learning. Somebody who married their
daughter off to a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, ועושה פרקמטיא לתלמיד חכם,
v'oseh prakmatya l'talmid chacham,
you have a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham be a partner with you
in business so you help provide him a פרנסה, parnassah, an easy
פרנסה, parnassah, just invest his money for him. ומהנה תלמידי חכמים מנכסיו,
u'mehaneh talmidei chachamim minechasav, you benefit, you give him a nice donation.
Okay, people that support תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. אבל תלמידי חכמים עצמן,
aval talmidei chachamim atzman, עין לא ראתה אלקים זולתך. Ayin lo ra'asa
Elokim zulasecha. For the reward of Torah learning itself, that, nobody has
had a vision of that. מאי עין לא ראתה? Mai ayin lo
ra'asa? Okay, now this is a very, it's almost a little like
after all of this
build-up about 'oh my God it's so amazing you won't even be
able to imagine it,' right? So now the גמרא Gemara says 'okay,
so like what's it gonna be?'
It's like a little like, you know, you have to think that
חז"ל Chazal had a sense of humor. It also feels like a
little puncturing, right? Where we're just like popping the balloon a little
bit. Okay, what does that mean? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Omar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, זה יין המשומר בענביו מששת ימי בראשית. zeh
yayin hameshummar be'anavav misheshes yemei bereishis. And also the answer is such
a letdown. It is like filtered wine that's been stored from ששת
ימי בראשית. sheshes yemei bereishis. Oh, you know what the vision is
that not even the prophets had a sight of? It's like some
rarest, most perfect
steak, you wouldn't believe it.
Like, so you have to imagine that this was a little like
humorous here, a little puncturing, that's the way I read it. Okay.
ריש לקיש אמר, Resh Lakish omar, זה עדן. zeh Eden. This is
Eden. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא ראתה עין מעולם, lo ra'asa ayin me'olam,
nobody has seen it. ואם תאמר אדם, v'im tomar Adam, what do
you mean? The first human lived in
Eden. No, הוא בגן, hu began, he lived only in the garden.
And we assume the garden means like it's the choicest part. But
he's saying no. ואם תאמר גן הוא עדן, v'im tomar gan hu
Eden, and if you think it's the same? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
ונהר יוצא מעדן להשקות את הגן. v'nahar yotzei me'Eden l'ashkos es hagan.
So it's the rest of Eden, that's where we're all gonna live.
Nobody has seen what Eden is and so on. Okay. Which again
is pretty funny because the Torah's vision of גן עדן Gan Eden
is pretty this-worldly. Okay, it's a beautiful place, right? But like the
visions of the prophets of what the messianic period are gonna be
certainly sound more ideal than the Torah's description of Eden, you know?
So it does seem a little like puncturing here at the end
of this thing. Okay, anyway. Yes, and in that man and God
talk...
Oh,
that's an interesting point.
You mean it's not the... physical aspect of עדן? Eden? I was
thinking about it because I was still being influenced by the points
about the wine, but you mean just the sense of God’s like
immediate presence. Yeah, that’s a good point. That’s a good point.
Somebody says it there in your footnote?
Yes, they say עדן Eden is the world some the righteous who
sit with their crowns and delight in the radiance.
Yeah, so that’s that other גמרא Gemara. about עולם הבא, Olam Ha-Ba,
right, which is, you know, the crowns on their head and directly
benefiting from the divine presence. Okay, so now it says like this.
Now that we are done with sort of laying out this whole
period of תחיית המתים, עולם הבא, Olam Ha-Ba. ימות המשיח, and so
on, because A, that’s what you don’t get if you don’t believe
in do the things or don’t believe in the things that are
mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, and the first person was the person
that doesn’t believe in עולם הבא, Olam Ha-ba now we get to
turn to the rest of the list. And the next big one
is האומר אין תורה מן השמים, Ha-Omer Ein Torah Min Ha-Shamayim, that
you say that תורה Torah is not from heaven. So let's take
a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. האומר אין תורה מן השמים, Ha-Omer
Ein Torah Min Ha-Shamayim, כי תנו רבנן, Ki Tanu Rabbanan, כי דבר
השם בזה, Ki Devar Hashem Bazah, because פסוק Pasuk, is כי דבר
השם בזה, Ki Devar Hashem Bazah, this person has like to
despise what how do they translate the word בזה, Bazah, degraded, demeaned,
the word of the Lord he has ביזוי, Bizui, anyway, you’ll tell
me what you got to it. Anyway, because the word of the
God he has despised or demeaned, הכרת תכרת הנפש ההיא עונה בה,
Hikairet Tikaret Ha-nefesh Ha-hi Avonah Bah,
that person shall be surely cut off, his sin is with him.
Right. Despise. Okay. So, but of course כרת Karet is not that
you don't have a portion in the world to come, plenty of
people get כרת, Karet, right, you know, I mean, there are plenty
of sins that you get כרת Karet for. So maybe it’s the
double language of הכרת תכרת, Hikairet Tikaret, you know, but even that
double language occurs elsewhere, sometimes we read הכרת תכרת Hikairet Tikaret to
mean עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba, So it’s not so explicit in the
פסוק, Pasuk but nevertheless this is the פסוק pasuk that serves as
the basis of this, that if you deny תורה מן השמים, Torah
Min Ha-Shamayim, you don’t have a portion in the world to come.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, כי דבר השם בזה מצותו הפר הכרת תכרת,
Ki Devar Hashem Bazah Mitzvato Hefer Hikairet Tikaret, זה האומר אין תורה
מן השמים, Zeh Ha-Omer Ein Torah Min Ha-Shamayim, that תורה Torah. is
not from heaven because you’re despising the דבר השם, Devar Hashem, the
word of God. You’re saying it’s not God’s word, it’s a human
being’s word. דבר אחר, Davar Acher, כי דבר השם
בזה, Ki Devar Hashem Bazah, זה אפיקורוס. Zeh Apikoros. This is the
אפיקורוס. Apikoros. Now, I need to pause here for a second because
everybody assumes אפיקורוס Apikoros means like a heretic, right, and therefore it
becomes a catchword for meaning anybody who doesn’t believe in what we
say the dogma of Judaism is. That is how רמב״ם Rambam reads
that word, because רמב״ם Rambam is the one that decided to catalog
and to not just catalog, but to articulate and try to systematize
and sort of identify, עיקרי אמונה, Ikarei Emunah,
fundamental dogma. And therefore רמב״ם Rambam said, so where does רמב״ם Rambam
get his hook, where do you get the hook that there’s a
list of dogma that you have to believe in it and so
on. So רמב״ם’s Rambam hook is this idea of אפיקורוס. Apikoros. We’ll
see about that more when we get to the line of אפיקורוס
Apikoros in the משנה. But that’s not what it means from the
גמרא’s Gemara perspective. From the גמרא’s Gemara perspective as we will see,
an אפיקורוס Apikoros is somebody who just acts in a disrespectful way
towards תורה Torah or towards תורה Torah scholars. Okay, like the גמרא
Gemara. says the classic definition of אפיקורוס Apikoros is מבזה תלמידי חכמים,
Mevazeh Talmidei Chachamim, which is exactly the word כי דבר השם בזה,
Ki Devar Hashem Bazah, מבזה, Mevazeh, somebody who acts like, you know,
in a demeaning way towards תורה Torah scholars. So that is showing
that you are despising and demeaning God’s words because the people that
are the embodiment or the representatives of God’s words, you’re acting towards
them in this, you know, highly disrespectful way. Okay, so that אפיקורוס.
Apikoros. So that explains the two lines in our משנה, אין תורה
מן השמים Ein Torah Min Ha-Shamayim and אפיקורוס. Apikoros. Both of those
are ways of showing disrespect, you know, and demeaning דבר השם. Devar
Hashem. דבר אחר, Davar Acher, כי דבר השם בזה, Ki Devar Hashem
Bazah, זה מגלה פנים בתורה. Zeh Megaleh Panim Ba-Torah. The one who
reveals faces in the תורה. Torah. Now what does this mean? So
normally, often, you would hear the phrase מגלה פנים בתורה שלא כהלכה,
Megaleh Panim Ba-Torah Shelo Ke-Halacha, and it’s read to mean somebody who
gives a who explicates the תורה Torah in a way that’s not
consistent with the הלכה. Halacha. I don’t know, let’s say somebody says
עין תחת עין Ayin Tachat Ayin means literal, the תורה Torah is
so terrible, it says עין תחת עין, Ayin Tachat Ayin, an eye
for an eye, and you’re interpreting it not the way הלכה Halacha
interprets it. Okay, but that is not what that phrase, you know,
means in the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara does not have the
phrase שלא כהלכה, Shelo Ke-Halacha, it doesn’t have it here, we’re going
to turn the page, it’s not going to have it for the
whole page. One place it has it, but it’s clearly a gloss,
that שלא כהלכה Shelo Ke-Halacha is like a later gloss of that
phrase. מגלה פנים Megaleh Panim does not mean you reveal an aspect
of the תורה Torah and you explicate it in a way that’s
wrong. מגלה פנים Megaleh Panim means גילוי פנים Gillui Panim means to
act
brazen, brazenly towards the תורה. Torah? So the way you relate to
the words of the תורה Torah, is in a brazen and disrespectful
and, you know, type of a way. How how do they translate
it in English? Acts insolently. Insolent towards the תורה Torah
at the gloss.
There you go. Okay, so that’s really that’s important to know because
often the phrase שלא כהלכה Shelo Ke-Halacha is tagged on but that
isn’t. and he has this sort of violated or loosened you know
the מצות, mitzvot, זה מפר ברית בשר. zeh meifer brit basar. This
is the one that has reversed the covenant of the flesh, people
that sort of do a reverse surgery to put back their foreskin.
הכרת תכרת, הכרת בעולם הזה, הכרת לעולם הבא, hikaret tikaret, hikaret baolam
hazeh, hikaret leolam haba, be cut off in this world and cut
off in the next world. By the way you note, right, it's
not like the גמרא Gemara here, right again I want to just
underscore this, that it's רמב"ם Rambam that develops this idea of like
dogma and if you don't believe you're an אפיקורוס apikoros and so
on. Like these types of things are a collection of issues of
attitudes and beliefs and actions, right? The person who acts disrespectfully to
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and the person who doesn't believe in
תורה מסיני Torah miSinai and the person who reverses his ברית מילה,
brit milah, right, that's a whole... we're not talking about dogma here,
right, we're talking about an attitude towards, you know, towards God, towards
Torah, you know, towards תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, towards your relationship with
God. Okay, so all of this is, you know, it's really רמב"ם
Rambam that turns this into an issue of dogma. Anyway,
where were we?
Mark Shapiro's line, I mean is that his direct channel what he
goes through in the...
Well, that's not,
Mark Shapiro's got other things he's dealing with, but the point that
I just made is not my חידוש chiddush or not Mark Shapiro's
חידוש chiddush either, you know, anyhow it's been noted for a long
time like, you know, even by, you know, like ראשונים Rishonim like
the חתם סופר, Chatam Sofer, I think it was the חתם סופר,
Chatam Sofer, he was very upset that רמב"ם Rambam sort of says,
you know, that there are thirteen עיקרי אמונה, ikarei emunah, the whole
thing. He says there's no thirteen עיקרי אמונה. ikarei emunah. The חתם
סופר Chatam Sofer said there's basically two עיקרי אמונה. ikarei emunah. Can
you get what the two... you really only have to believe two
things and everything else sort of follows. What would these two things
be? השם? Hashem? God and Torah? Okay, God exists and God gave
the Torah. Anything else, especially if you throw in תורה שבעל פה,
Torah shebe'al peh, then you got everything. Anyway, but the idea to
systematize it to create this identity of an אפיקורוס, apikoros, this idea
of a list of dogma, like it's not in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay. Okay. הכרת תכרת, הכרת בעולם הזה, הכרת לעולם הבא. hikaret tikaret,
hikaret baolam hazeh, hikaret leolam haba. מכאן אמר רבי אלעזר המודעי, mikan
amar Rabbi Eliezer HaModai, from here רבי אלעזר המודעי Rabbi Eliezer HaModai
says in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, המחלל את הקדשים והמבזה את המועדות,
hamachalel et hakodashim vehamivazeh et hamo'adot, somebody who desecrates the sacrifices and
disrespects, again the word מבזה, mivazeh, the מועדות, mo'adot, which רש"י Rashi
says means חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, that you that because that's maybe
the one that's more vulnerable that you'll disrespect it. והמפר בריתו של
אברהם אבינו, vehamapher brito shel Avraham Avinu, somebody who reverses the ברית
מילה, brit milah, והמגלה פנים בתורה, vehamigaleh panim baTorah, here's the שלא
כהלכה shelo kehalacha stuck in but it's not going to be there,
one who acts brazenly towards the Torah, והמלבין פני חברו ברבים, vehamalbin
pnei chaveiro barabbim, somebody who shames his friend in the masses, אף
על פי שיש בידו תורה ומעשים טובים אין לו חלק לעולם הבא,
af al pi sheyesh beyado Torah uma'asim tovim ein lo chelek laolam
haba, no matter how many מצות mitzvot you have, you won't have
a portion in the world to come. Now is all of that
learned out from this פסוק pasuk of כי דבר השם בזה? ki
dvar Hashem bazah? It'd be interesting to try to stick this in,
like how are the sacrifices דבר השם? dvar Hashem? I mean, okay,
they're something that's sanctified by God, right, and the מועד mo'ed is
time that's sanctified by God. How about מלבין פני חברו? malbin pnei
chaveiro? Is that because human beings are created בצלם אלוקים? betzelem Elokim?
So all these are ways of desecrating and being מבזה mivazeh things
that are godly? That would seem to be the case and רש"י
Rashi sort of seems to read it that way. Okay. So תניא
אידך, tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא, braita, כי דבר השם
בזה, ki dvar Hashem bazah, זה אמר אין תורה מן השמים, zeh
omer ein Torah min hashamayim, Torah's not from heaven. ואפילו אמר כל
התורה כלה מן השמים חוץ מפסוק אחד, ve'afilu amar kol haTorah kullah
min hashamayim chutz mipasuk echad, everything except for one verse because it's
דבר השם, dvar Hashem, even one word of God. Okay? So even
if you deny one פסוק pasuk, שלא אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא אלא
משה מפי עצמו, shelo amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu ela Moshe mipi atzmo,
but Moshe said it on his own, he didn't say it through
God, זה כי דבר השם בזה, zeh ki dvar Hashem bazah, that
is to denigrate, to despise the word of God. ואפילו אמר כל
התורה כלה מן השמים חוץ מדקדוק זה, ve'afilu amar kol haTorah kullah
min hashamayim chutz midekduk zeh, from one little inference, מקל וחומר זה,
mikal vachomer zeh, one little קל וחומר kal vachomer that, you know,
a rabbinic interpretation which gets to real questions, right? Because what does
that mean? Is every rabbinic interpretation directly from God? Don't the rabbis
apply certain hermeneutic principles and then derive it on their own? Is
it only the stuff that we're supposed to understand was given over
at הר סיני, Har Sinai, that part of the תורה שבעל פה?
Torah shebe'al peh? Okay, maybe you mean that you deny the rabbis'
authority to interpret. Anyway, חוץ מגזרה שוה זו, chutz migezeirah shavah zo,
everything except for this one linking of the verses, גזרה שוה gezeirah
shavah at least is supposed to be like given over from הר
סיני, Har Sinai, זהו כי דבר השם בזה. zehu ki dvar Hashem
bazah. The מהרש"א Maharsha says that the emphasis here is again on
the word דבר dvar and here it's דבר davar as opposed to
something that is written. It's not only if you deny a written
פסוק, pasuk which is not just a דיבור, dibbur, not just speech,
but actually כתב, ktav, even if you deny part of the Oral
Torah, just the oral part of it, the דיבור dibbur part of
it. תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, האי רבי מאיר
אומר כל הלומד תורה ואינו מלמדה, hai Rabbi Meir omer kol halomed
Torah ve'eino melamdah, if you learn Torah and don't teach it, זהו
כי דבר השם בזה. zehu ki dvar Hashem bazah. My מהרש"א Maharsha
*Maharsha* says again because you can learn it without verbalizing, but to
teach you have to verbalize. So to not teach it is to
be מבזה *mevaze*, to be demeaning, you know, whatever despising of the
דבר ה' *Devar Hashem*, of the verbalizing of God's word. Again though
notice that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is just easily slipping between issues
of faith and issues of attitude and issues of action and so
on. Okay. רבי נתן אומר *Rebbi Nasan Omer*, כל המשנה שאינו משגיח
על המשנה *Kol Hamishneh She'eino Mashgiach Al Hamishnah*, this applies to anybody
who's not careful on the משנה *Mishnah* to repeat it and to
learn it over again, you know, again because the משנה *Mishnah* explains
what the פסוקים pesukim *Pesukim* mean and so on. רבי נהוראי אומר
*Rebbi Nehorai Omer*, כל שאפשר לעסוק בתורה ואינו עוסק *Kol She'efshar La'asok
BaTorah Ve'eino Osek*, somebody who basically can learn תורה Torah *Torah* and
instead you decide, you know, you're going to just read a novel
or watch TV. Okay? So you're not showing, you know, the fact
that you're giving priority to other things over דבר ה' *Devar Hashem*.
That's כי דבר ה' בזה ki devar Hashem baza. *Ki Devar Hashem
Baza*. רבי ישמעאל אומר *Rebbi Yishmael Omer*, זה עובד עבודת כוכבים *Ze
Oved Avodas Kochavim*. Okay, that's so funny, like, we're trying to say
even small little things can be כי דבר ה' בזה ki devar
Hashem baza *Ki Devar Hashem Baza*. He says, whoa, like, if you
want to really, like, okay, I don't approve of all that other
stuff, but it's, you know, if you want to really talk about
the punishment of this פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*, if we're going to interpret
it of אין לו חלק לעולם הבא *Ein Lo Chelek Le'olam HaBa*,
right, let's let's limit it to stuff that's the real weighty, עובד
עבודה זרה *Oved Avodah Zarah*. מאי משמע *Mai Mashma*? This is the
one thing the גמרא *Gemara* will say, where do you get עבודה
זרה *Avodah Zarah* in the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*? Everything else is סברא
*Sevara*. Where do you get עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah*? דתני דבי רבי
ישמעאל *Detani Debei Rebbi Yishmael*, כי דבר ה' בזה ki devar Hashem
baza. *Ki Devar Hashem Baza*, זה המבזה דיבור *Ze HaMevaze Dibbur* שנאמר
She-ne'emar: לו למשה מסיני *Shenemar Lo LeMoshe MiSinai*. You are rejecting the
prime דיבור *Dibbur* of God. What is that prime דיבור *Dibbur*? אנכי
ה' אלהיך *Anochi Hashem Elokecha*, it's also the one that we all
heard. Okay. לא יהיה לך אלהים אחרים *Lo Yihiyeh Lecha Elohim Acheirim*.
Okay, so that is דבר ה' *Devar Hashem*, the דבר ה' *Devar
Hashem* that you directly heard. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר *Rebbi Yehoshua
Ben Korcha Omer*, כל הלומד תורה Torah. ואינו חוזר עליה דומה לאדם
שזורע ואינו קוצר *Kol Halomed Torah Ve'eino Chozer Aleha Domeh LeAdam SheZoreia
Ve'eino Kotzer*. Since we're talking about that if you don't, like, repeat
it, like, what do we say you don't repeat? You we said
אינו משגיח על המשנה *Eino Mashgiach Al HaMishnah*. Okay. So in a
similar way, if you sort of learn it but you don't do
חזרה chazara, *Chazarah*, right, it's like planting without harvesting. Like, what good
is it going to do? The seed is just going to rot
in the ground. If you want to cultivate it and make it
take root and make it grow and make it be something lasting,
you have to do חזרה chazarah, *Chazarah*. Okay. רבי יהושע *Rebbi Yehoshua*—and
that could be a type of a דבר ה' בזה *Devar Hashem
Baza* as well—if you value it, you're going to learn it again
and again. רבי יהושע אומר *Rebbi Yehoshua Omer*, כל הלומד תורה Torah
ומשכחה *Kol Halomed Torah U'Meshach'cha*, anybody who learns תורה Torah? *Torah* and
forgets it—not—so that would be an expected outcome of not doing חזרה
*Chazarah*, but this is the actual fact that you actually have forgotten
it—דומה לאשה שיולדת וקוברת *Domeh Le'ishah SheYoledes VeKoveres*. Oi, what a terrible
image. A woman who gives birth and then buries her child. Okay?
That's completely—it's not just, you know, if you plant seeds and you
don't cut—and you don't cut them, stuff might still grow, you know,
who knows, maybe, you know, but here it's like it's all—it's completely
lost. So what's the point? Why did you go through all—so if
you think about the whole image before about חבלי לידה של משיח
*Chevlei Leidah Shel Mashiach*, like, why do you go through all this
effort, you know? You know, there's actually—what is it called, like, ROI,
return on investment? Like, you put in all this effort to produce
something, you know, it's actually sometimes, like, less effort is required to
sustain it and to actually, like, you know, the follow-through.
But often we don't bother with the follow-through. Why did you go
through all this effort if you're just going to not, you know,
do the little bit that's going to be required to sustain it
and then you're going to let it all, like, you know, get—go
to waste? רבי עקיבא אומר *Rebbi Akiva Omer*, רבי עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva*
says, זמר בכל יום זמר בכל יום *Zemer Bechol Yom Zemer Bechol
Yom*, that your תורה Torah. *Torah* should be a song every day.
Now
the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* says maybe זמר *Zemer* again in this image
of planting means, like, זומר *Zomer* means, like, to cut the weeds,
you know, to prune, not to cut the weeds, to prune, like,
you know, which, like, sort of every day you should be tending
to what you planted and pruning it and, like, distilling it and
so on. But it's better to read it, I think, as a
song. The way you keep תורה Torah. *Torah* going is, so either
literally or figuratively, like a song. You do it over and over
and over again. The same way, you know, you get a jingle
in your head and you keep on singing it or whatever, so
if you sort of make it like a song and you say
it over and over again, that way it'll stick with you. But
it also could literally mean that you actually do, like, have a
ניגון *Niggun* to it, you know, like in the חדרים *Chadarim* they
used to have a ניגון *Niggun* to the learning, and you know,
and that's—we remember things, right? We remember songs probably better than we
remember, in terms of the words of songs, anything else because they're
associated with music and it sticks in our head. Okay, so that's
the way that you would get—you want to say something about that?
It could also just be with joy.
Oh,
with joy? Okay, that could be too, but although with the context
here, I think is about, like, remembering it and sustaining it. So,
but you mean maybe the joy also is a way in which
it sort of, you know, reinforces your desire, right, to keep it
up and to keep on learning it. Okay, right. Actually, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says that. If you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, היה מסדר
לימודך אף על פי שסדורה בפיך כזמר *Haya Mesader Limudcha Af Al
Pi SheSedurah Beficha KeZemer*, so, you know, constantly, like, repeat it like
a song, והוא יגרום לך שתהא לעולם הבא בשמחה ובשירים *VeHu Yigrom
Lecha SheTehe Le'olam HaBa BeSimcha U'BeShirim*. So there you go, Gloria, with
joy. Okay. אמר רב יצחק Yitzchak בר אבדימי מאי קרא *Amar Rav
Yitzchak Bar Avdimi Mai Kra*, what is the verse— שנאמר She-ne'emar: as
it says, נפש עמל עמלה לו כי אכף עליו פיהו. nefesh amal
amla lo ki akaf alav pihu.
If you put in the effort, then it will work for you,
you know like they say like having your money work for you,
having your תורה Torah. work for you. If you make it into
a song, then it will work for you. So רש"י Rashi says,
מפני שעמל בתורה תורה עומלת לו. mipnei she-amal ba-Torah Torah omelet lo.
So what does it mean it will work for him? You'll get
reward from it? Does it mean that it'll like the מהרש"א says,
it means in עולם הבא you'll be revealed the hidden secrets of
the תורה? Torah, But I also think, you know how like it's
this sort of the percolating effect? Like, you know, you're trying to
figure something out and you can't get to it and then you
go and you take a little walk, you know, to get a
cup of coffee and all of a sudden like the meaning hits
you like because you're not conscious of it, but part of your
brain is still processing it? So I think that's how I'd like
to read it. Like if you're singing it and going over it
and whatever, then even when you're not talking in the תורה, Torah
it's working for you. It's going on somewhere in your head and
it's actually processing and, you know, maybe even revealing things that you
weren't thinking of when you were sort of consciously working on it.
Okay. So, נפש עמל עמלה לו כי אכף עליו פיהו, nefesh amal
amla lo ki akaf alav pihu,
because his mouth has אכף עליו, akaf alav, which we're going to
read רש"י Rashi says it means like an אוכף, ukaf, like a
saddle. הוא עמל במקום זה ותורתו עמלה לו במקום אחר, hu amal
be-makom zeh ve-Torato amla lo be-makom acher, you're working here,
and you've got your תורה Torah. working for you somewhere else in
עולם הבא, in the back of your head, whatever it is. אמר
רבי אליעזר כל אדם לעמל נברא, Amar Rabbi Eliezer kol adam le-amal
nivra,
every person is created for work. Okay, this is like, isn't that
a פסוק pasuk. in like קהלת? Kohelet? Anyway, שנאמר She-ne'emar: or איוב,
Iyov, there you go, איוב, Iyov, not קהלת. Kohelet. כי אדם לעמל
יולד, ki adam le-amal yulad, a person is created for labor, for
work. איני יודע אם לעמל פה נברא אם לעמל מלאכה, eini yode'a
im le-amal peh nivra im le-amal melacha, does that mean to do
like work with the פה peh נברא nivra
or to do, you know, physical labor? So you could sort of
say, like, you know, what type of job do you want to
get? Do you want to get a job that's physical or the
one that's intellectual? But here it means is it work in the
field of תורה Torah, or work in the sort of field of
labor? Okay. So, נברא. nivra. כשהוא אומר כי אכף עליו פיהו, keshe-hu
omer ki akaf alav pihu,
because his mouth is אכף, akaf, רש"י Rashi says it means like
a saddle, like you sort of like you put it on like,
I don't know, like you connect, you know, you deeply connect to
it. הוי אומר לעמל פה נברא, hevei omer le-amal peh nivra, that
it's the labor of the mouth, which obviously as we're getting to
תורה. Torah, ועדיין איני יודע אם לעמל תורה אם לעמל שיחה, ve-adayin
eini yode'a im le-amal Torah im le-amal sicha, does that mean that
you're supposed to devote yourself to תורה Torah. or maybe you're supposed
to devote yourself to, I don't know, conversation? You're supposed to be
a speechwriter or something, okay? Or just, you know, obviously, or to
just say it means foolish talk, but whatever it is, it might
be something verbal, but how do you know it means תורה? Torah?
כשהוא אומר לא ימוש ספר התורה הזה מפיך, keshe-hu omer lo yamush
sefer ha-Torah ha-zeh mipicha, and there's the word פה, peh, let this
ספר תורה sefer Torah not be removed from your mouth. הוי אומר
לעמל תורה נברא, hevei omer le-amal Torah nivra, you're created to spend
your time talking and learning in תורה. Torah. וזהו דאמר רבא, ve-haynu
de-amar Rava, this is what רבא Rava says, כולהו גופי דרופתקי נינהו,
kulhu gufei deruftaki ninhu,
all people are created for, רש"י Rashi: says it means for like
as laborers. טובי לדזכי דהוי דרופתקי
דאורייתא. tovei le-dizakei de-havei deruftaki d'Oraisa. Good are the ones that merit
that they become workers in תורה. Torah. Okay. So back now to
this idea of constantly reviewing your תורה. Torah It's fascinating, I've got
to say. In something that was about תורה מן השמים, Torah min
ha-shamayim, we're spending all of this time talking about, like, you know,
not forgetting your תורה, Torah, doing חזרה, etc. And again, it gets
to the point that the גמרא is less interested in dogma per
se and more as it's interested in relationship and attitudes and actions
and so on. So therefore, this is the opposite of כי דבר
ה' בזה. ki devar Hashem baza. The opposite of כי דבר ה'
בזה Ki devar Hashem bazah? is how do you invest your energies
and your time to show your love of תורה Torah, and to
own תורה. Torah All right. So now, ונואף אשה חסר לב, ve-no'ef
isha chaser lev, a man who commits adultery is lacking of heart.
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, זה הלומד תורה לפרקים. zeh ha-lomed
Torah l'prakim. This is like somebody who learns תורה, Torah you know,
every now and then when you get a chance, okay? It's not
like you have a marriage to תורה, Torah which is an ongoing
thing. Like, you know, it's like a mistress. Okay, so and that
does not lead to a deep, meaningful, you know, relationship. שנאמר, She-ne'emar:
כי נעים כי תשמרם בבטנך יכונו יחדיו על שפתיך. ki na'im ki
tishmerem be-vitnecha yikonu yachdav al sfatecha. For
they are pleasant when you keep them in your belly; then they
will be established well on your lips. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, והנפש
אשר תעשה ביד רמה. ve-ha-nefesh asher ta'aseh be-yad rama. Okay.
So now, so that's sort of like the flip of כי דבר
ה' בזה. Now we're getting back to examples of כי דבר ה'
בזה. The person that does it with an outstretched arm. זה מנשה
בן חזקיה. zeh Menashe ben Chizkiyah. That's מנשה בן חזקיה. Menashe ben
Chizkiyah. שהיה יושב ודורש באגדות של דופי. she-haya yoshev ve-doresh b'agadot shel
dofi. He was sitting and sort of, you know, expounding on nonsense
types of a... like
teachings and sermons. אמר, וכי לא היה לו למשה לכתוב אלא ואחות
לוטן תמנע ותמנע היתה פילגש לאליפז? v'chi lo haya lo le-Moshe lichtov
ela va-achot Lotan Timna ve-Timna hayta pilegesh l'Elifaz? Why did משה have
to write, you know, that לוטן's Lotan sister was תמנע Timna and
תמנע Timna was the פילגש pilegesh of אליפז? Elifaz? Like, who needs
all the generate... like even if it maybe had to say that
because we want to know, there's questions which part of the פסוק
is he questioning. Why do we have to know all... all the
wives of עשו Esav mentioned, or maybe what he was saying was,
why do we have to know the whole generations, the whole descendant,
way the מהרש"א explained
it, that this... that this... you know? Like what's the need of
that whole context? Okay. Now also, וילך ראובן בימי קציר חטים וימצא
דודאים בשדה. Vayeilech Reuven bimei ketzir chitim vayimtza dudaim basadeh.
Why does it have to say that he went and he found
these mandrakes and what exactly is bothering him? I mean it's part
of the whole story about לאה Leah and whatever. Maybe what's bothering
him is again that the whole idea of the mandrakes I mean
that would be the common theme here is seen as something like
a type of an aphrodisiac maybe. So maybe also the idea of
פילגש pilegesh maybe what's bothering him is like why is it dealing
with these type of sexual issues you know? Anyway, why did it
need all these stories? Okay, יצתה בת קול ואמרה לו. Yatzta bat
kol ve'amra lo. So notice again he didn't say you know now
the question is was he saying God didn't say it? Moses said
it? Because he sort of says וכי היה לו למשה לכתוב Vechai
hayah lo l'Moshe lichtov like why did Moses write it? So is
his sin that he doesn't believe that the תורה Torah מסיני or
his sin more like כי דבר ה' בזה? Like he's just being
disrespectful to the words of תורה. Torah. Whether he's saying why did
Moses write it or why did God write it, either way he's
saying like this is silly. Why is this in the תורה? Torah,
Alright and that seems to be more the גמרא's point. Okay.
רש"י Rashi says שכתב משה יש לו משה שלא אותה. Shekatav Moshe
yesh lo Moshe shelo otah. But again the question is is the
point here denying that God wrote it or more questioning you know
you know just being disrespectful in general? Anyway so יצתה בת קול
ואמרה לו. Yatzta bat kol ve'amra lo. So a heavenly voice came
out and said תשב באחיך תדבר בבן אמך תתן דופי. Teshev be'achicha
tedaber beven imecha titen dofi.
Will you speak against your brother, speak against you know your mother's
son and sort of ascribe דופי dofi ascribe like not ascribe foolishness.
So how how could you say such a thing about you know
אלה עשית והחרשתי? Eileh asita vehecherashti?
If you have done this and I would have remained silent דמית
dimita or I had remained silent היות אהיה כמוך. heyot eheyeh chamocha.
You thought that I was being agreeing with you because I wasn't
protesting. אוכיחך. Ochichecha. This is actually very good about like silence what's
that you know being a silent enabler not standing up all you
know all evil needs to prosper is for good men to remain
silent. So this is a פסוק. Because I was silent you thought
I was one of you. אוכיחך Ochichecha I will I will remonstrate
you ואערכה לעיניך ve'erecha l'einecha and I will sort of you know
sort of lay out my argument against you. Okay so the בת
קול bat kol said like how dare you suggest such a thing.
ועליו מפורש בקבלה Ve'alav meforash bakabalah הוי משכי העון בחבלי השוא וכעבות
העגלה חטאה. Hoi moshchei he'avon bechavlei hashav uche'avot ha'agalah chata'ah. Woe to
those who drag the iniquity with ropes of nothingness and like the
the cords of the of the wagon they drag sin. מאי כעבות
העגלה? Mai ke'avot ha'agalah? What does that mean? אמר רבי אסי Amar
Rabi Assi יצר הרע בתחילה דומה לחוט של כוביא Yeitzer hara betichilah
domeh lachut shel kuvya originally the יצר הרע Yeitzer hara is like
a spider's like a string of a spider's web ולבסוף דומה כעבות
העגלה ul'vasof domeh ke'avot ha'agalah and it becomes if you sort of
allow it to to continue you know it it gets to be
as thick as a cord of a wagon. דאתא למאי אחות
לוטן תמנע De'ata lemai achot Lotan Timna which basically seems to be
the point like
how's that anyway relevant here? It seems the relevance here is is
that if you allow yourself a little type of disrespectful attitude like
it's one thing to say like I want to understand why God
wrote this in the תורה. Torah You're allowed to ask those questions.
What is the purpose of this? Right? But if you start to
say like it's foolish, it's stupid, this doesn't belong in the תורה.
Right? So even if that seems like it's a small little thing
like it says alright it's one thing you said whatever. But that
attitude can like grow and develop and so on and it leads
to a deep sense of rejection you know and disrespect. Okay so
now the גמרא says okay now let's discuss what the purpose of
those פסוקים are since we're talking about it. דאתא למאי אחות לוטן
תמנע מאי היא? De'ata lemai achot Lotan Timna mai hi? Why was
it mentioned? תמנע בת מלכים הויא. Timna bat melachim havaia. She was
a daughter of kings. דכתיב Dechtiv אלוף לוטן אלוף תמנע. Aluf Lotan
Aluf Timna. וכל אלוף מלכותא בלא תגא Vechol aluf malchuta bela taga
and any אלוף aluf means like a king without the crown. Okay
so it's a certain position of leadership. בעיא לאיגורי. Ba'aya l'igurei.
So she wanted to convert even though she was the daughter of
kings of the חורי. Chori. אתאי אצל אברהם יצחק ויעקב ולא קיבלוה.
Atai eitzel Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov velo kibluha. So she went to אברהם
Avraham יצחק and יעקב. Yaakov. They refused to accept her. You know
you're from these non-Jew whatever. הלכה והיתה פילגש לאליפז בן עשו. Halacha
vehayta pilegesh l'Elifaz ben Esau.
So then she became a פילגש pilegesh to אליפז בן עשו. Elifaz
ben Esau. אמרה מוטב שתהא שפחה לאומה זו ולא תהא גבירה לאומה
אחרת. Amra mutav shetehei shifchah l'umah zo velo tehei gvirah l'umah acheret.
I'd rather be a maidservant just a פילגש pilegesh to this nation
rather than being you know you know a great you know a
great mistress in some other nation a great woman in some other
nation. נפק מינה עמלק. Nafak minah Amalek. And the daughter right of
of of this right and תמנע Timna was concubine to אליפז בן
עשו Elifaz ben Esau and תמנע Timna was concubine to אליפז בן
עשו Elifaz ben Esau and she bore to אליפז Elifaz עמלק Amalek
and אליפז בן עשו Elifaz ben Esau and she bore to אליפז
Elifaz עמלק Amalek which was the nation that caused all of that
you know attack the Jews and represents evil so דצערינהו לישראל detza'arinhu
l'Yisrael that afflicted the Jewish people. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? Why
why did that emerge from her? She didn't do anything wrong. She
wanted to be connected to the Jewish people. So why did עמלק
Amalek come from her? דלא איבעי להו לרחקה. Delo ibei lehu lerachakah.
We brought it on ourselves. We shouldn't have pushed her away. Okay
if you look at רש"י לרחקה. lerachakah. Top רש"י on the left-hand
column: מתחת כנפי השכינה, Mitachat kanfei hashchina, שהיה להם לגיירה. She-haya lahem
legayera. They should have agreed to convert her. So this גמרא's quoted
by people
who talk about the attitude we have of creating all these really
impossible high thresholds for conversion; sincere people want to convert, there are
consequences to be paid when we don't do that.
Anyway, let's just finish this, ויילך ראובן בימי קציר חיטים, Vayelech Reuven
bimei ktzir chitim, so let's talk about that פסוק. אמר רב בר
רב יצחק אמר רב: Amar Rav Bar Rav Yitzchak Amar Rav: מטובתן
של צדיקים שאין פושטים ידיהם בגזל. Mitovatan shel tzadikim she-ein poshtim yedeihem
begazel. The point of writing that is that he went when they
were cutting the wheat and at that time, it was allowed for
him to go into other fields, presumably it wasn't considered trespassing at
that time. Okay, so if you look at רש"י: לאחר שקצרו השדה
הכל פורשים להיכנס בתוך שדה חבריהם. L'achar shekatzru hasadeh hakol porshim lehikanes
betoch sadeh chavreihem.
After they did the harvesting, nobody minds if you cut through their
field. So that's why it emphasized that that's why he went at
that time. Okay. וימצא דודאים בשדה. Vayimtzah dudaim basadeh. מאי דודאים? Mai
dudaim?
What are these דודאים? dudaim? We normally translate them as mandrakes. אמר
רב יברוחי. Amar Rav yavrochei. לוי אמר סיגלי. Levi amar sigli. רבי
יונתן אמר סביסקי. Rabbi Yonatan amar savisky.
I have no idea what any of those things are. Did they
translate them in your English?
All right, סיגלי sigli and סביסקי, savisky, looks
like.
All right, well
there's some type of flower.
It says רש"י says סיגלי sigli is a violet.
Violet, oh right, that is what סיגלי sigli is I think in
modern Hebrew. Okay, let's just read a little bit more and
the other is some certain type of spice, okay, סביסקי. savisky.
אמר רבי אלכסנדרי, Amar Rabbi Alexandri,
back to the positive, since we were mentioning the negative. כל העוסק
בתורה לשמה, Kol ha-osek ba-Torah lishmah, if you learn תורה for the
right reason, משים שלום בפמליא של מעלה ובפמליא של מטה. Mashim shalom
be-pamalia shel ma'ala u-be-pamalia shel mata. You make peace in the family
above and the family below, in heaven and on earth, שנאמר: She-ne'emar:
או יחזק במעוזי יעשה שלום לי שלום יעשה לי. O yachazek be-maozi
ya'aseh shalom li shalom ya'aseh li. Two types of peace,
peace above, peace below. רבא אמר: Rava amar: כאילו בנה פלטרין של
מעלה ושל מטה. Ke-ilu bana paltarin shel ma'ala ve-shel mata. Like you
built a palace above and below. שנאמר: She-ne'emar: ואשים דברי בפיך. Va-asim
devarai be-ficha. That,
so my words in your mouth, going back to the whole word
of פה, peh, repeating it, loving it, doing חזרה, ובצל ידי כיסיתיך
לנטוע שמים וליסוד ארץ, Ub-tzel yadi kisiticha linto'a shamayim velisod aretz, to
plant heaven and to found the earth.
So basically if you really love it and connect to it, you
both serve God and you serve this world. רבי יוחנן אמר: Rabbi
Yochanan amar: אף מגין על כל העולם כולו. Af megin al kol
ha-olam kulo. Protects the entire world. שנאמר: ובצל ידי כיסיתיך. Ub-tzel yadi
kisiticha.
So the power of learning תורה, this is the opposite of מבזה
דבר ה', Mevaze d'var Hashem, is that this is what keeps the
world protected, this is what sustains the world. לוי אמר: Levi amar:
אף מקרב את הגאולה. Af me-karev et ha-geulah. You bring close the
redemption. שנאמר: ולאמר לציון עמי אתה. Velomar le-Tzion ami atah. ריש לקיש
אמר: Resh Lakish amar: כל המלמד את בן חברו תורה, Kol ha-melamed
et ben chavero Torah,
if you teach your friend's son תורה, מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו עשאו.
Ma'ala alav ha-katuv ke-ilu asa'o.
It's like you created this person because you gave them a spiritual
life. Presumably your friend wasn't able to teach him and you did.
שנאמר: ואת הנפש אשר עשו בחרן. V'et ha-nefesh asher asu ve-Charan. The
souls that they made. So normally it means we say converted or
whatever, but here it means like if they made because they spread
God's word to them, they told them about God. So you know
it's like you gave them a spiritual birth, you made them born
again, right? So, רבי אלעזר אמר: Rabbi Eleazar amar: כאילו עשאן לדברי
תורה. Ke-ilu asan l'divrei Torah.
You've sort of turned them into תורה words, you've like made them
walking תורה or you yourself have participated in making the תורה a
real thing by spreading it. If you love תורה so much that
you want to spread it and bring it in the world, you
helped to create תורה. Okay. שנאמר: ושמרתם את דברי הברית הזאת ועשיתם
אותם. Ushmartem et divrei ha-brit ha-zot va-asitem otam.
You will not just perform them but you will make them, you
make the words of this covenant by teaching them. ורבא אמר: Ve-Rava
amar: כאילו עשאו לעצמו. Ke-ilu asa'o l'atzmo. It's like you made yourself.
By teaching and spreading תורה, you have transformed yourself in the process.
שנאמר: ועשיתם אותם, Va-asitem otam, אל תקרי אותם אלא אתם. Al tikrei
otam ela atem.
You make yourself. אמר רבי אבהו: Amar Rabbi Abbahu: כל המעשה את
חברו לדבר מצווה. Kol ha-ma'aseh et chavero le-dvar mitzvah.
Now this is not exactly connected but we're talking about making others
and making yourself, so we're shifting a little from the תורה focus.
Anybody who encourages or compels his friend to do a מצווה, mitzvah,
מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו עשאו. ma'ala alav ha-katuv ke-ilu asa'o. It's like
you did it. שנאמר: ומטך אשר הכית בו
את היאור. U-matcha asher hikita bo et ha-Ye'or. וכי משה הכה? V'chi
Moshe hikah? Was it Moshe the one who smote? והלא אהרן הכה?
Ve-halo Aharon hikah? It was אהרן. Aharon. אלא לומר לך: Ela lomar
lacha: כל המעשה את חברו לדבר מצווה, kol ha-ma'aseh et chavero le-dvar
mitzvah, if you make your friend do a מצווה, mitzvah, מעלה עליו
הכתוב כאילו עשאו, ma'ala alav ha-katuv ke-ilu asa'o, like you did it.
So that was a little bit of a digression.
Okay, we will pick up tomorrow with seeing who is the אפיקורוס
apikoros and I will just tell you as I've been telling you
it is not the apostate and it is not a word in
the גמרא that means somebody who does not believe in the עיקרי
אמונה ikarei emunah which I'm about to tell you what they are,
which is what רמב"ם did to that word, okay, but we will
see about that tomorrow.